George England Papers VHP2006/8
CCSU Veterans History Project
George W. England Papers
Bulk, 1943-1946
1943 - 1946, 2006
VHP2006/8
CCSU Veterans History Project
37.0 Digital objects 1 interview DVD
This collection details George England's experience serving with U.S. Navy during World War II. The collection contains video of an oral history interview, personal documents, newspaper clipping, and photographs.
England, George, 1942 -
Biographical/Historical note
George W. England joined the U.S. Navy in June of 1943 and attended basic training in Sampson, NY. After basic training he continued on to Memphis, TN to train at the aviation center and naval airport. After this training he volunteered for additional training as an aerial gunner. He was then transferred to Jacksonville, FL to complete an additional 8 weeks of training. It was there that he became part of a crew of 2 pilots, a navigator, an instructor, and 5 students. England then went to Hutchinson, KS where he became a member of the crew on a B-24, which was part of the VPB 111th Patrolled Bombing Squadron. The squadron was known as the "liberator" patrol-bombers. The crew was sent to San Diego, and then Hawaii before flying overseas. When they received their orders to go overseas, the crew of England's B-24 decided that they needed a mascot, so they adopted a German Sheppard that flew alongside them in every mission. They flew missions to Hong Kong, the Philippines, Okinawa, Singapore, and Borneo, in which their main objective was to search for downed aircraft, ships, and submarines. The planes in England's unit faced regular combat, and attempts were often made to shoot them down. England was discharged in April of 1946. He returned home to Connecticut where he returned to school and then later worked at IBM until he retired. He remains active in the Avon post of the VFW.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for Research
Custodial History note
All manuscripts and photographs donated were digitized and digitally preserved. The donor retained all original manuscripts and photographs.
Online Access
An online exhibition of this veteran's papers can be accessed at project's website
United States. Navy. Patrol Bombing Squadron 111.; B-24 bomber; Hawaii; Hutchinson (Kan.); Okinawa-shi (Japan); Philippines; Sampson Naval Training Station (Sampson, N.Y.); San Diego (Calif.); United States. Navy -- Aviation; World War, 1939-1945 -- Campaigns -- Japan -- Okinawa Island; World War, 1939-1945 -- Personal narratives, American
- Series I: Personal Papers, VHP2006/8.I
  - Certificate of completion of the Aviation Machinist Mate course, Feb. 19, 1944; VHP2006/8.I.1
  - Letter congratulating George England as he receives Navy award, Dec. 13, 1946; VHP2006/8.I.2
  - Graduation Certificate from Aerial Gunnery School Jacksonville, FL, Apr. 24, 1944; VHP2006/8.I.3
  - Certificate of Rabies Vaccination for "Sheba", a mascot dog, upon return to US, Sep. 17, 1946; VHP2006/8.I.4
  - Interview synopsis, Apr. 8, 2006; VHP2006/8.I.5
- Series II: Publications, VHP2006/8.II
  - Manchester Evening Herald article about George England receiving awards, circa 1946; VHP2006/8.II.1
  - Article from CTNOW.com website on six WW II veterans (including George England), May 27, 2004; VHP2006/8.II.2; 5.0 Digital objects
- Series III: Multi-Media, VHP2006/8.III
  - Subseries A: Still Images, VHP2006/8.III
    - U.S. Navy Training Station. Sampson, NY, Jul. 29, 1943; VHP2006/8.III.1
      General note
      George England on 4th row - 5th from the right.
    - Naval Air Technical School. Memphis, TN, 1944; VHP2006/8.III.2
      George England on 3rd row - 1st on the left.
    - Arrived at Leyte, Philippines, Feb. 1945; VHP2006/8.III.3
      Louis Smith (Lewiston, Maine) on bed Mel Buholzar standing Cots and tents provided by (Construction Battalion) CB’s Netting on bed was loaded with mosquitoes
    - George England (left) and Bill Weir. Leyte, Philippines., 1945; VHP2006/8.III.4
    - George and Sheba next to their tent, 1945; VHP2006/8.III.5
    - Navy B-24 Liberator Waiting for the co-pilot and navigator to arrive in a Jeep. Leyte, Philippine, 1945; VHP2006/8.III.6
    - George England on top of B-24's engine, 1945; VHP2006/8.III.7
    - Mel Buholzar operating B-24's side machine gun, airborne on a mission., 1945; VHP2006/8.III.8
    - Sheba and George England in B-24 cockpit, Just checked plane - ready to leave, 1945; VHP2006/8.III.9
    - George England (left) and Mel Buholzar cleaning the 50 caliber guns from the mission the day before. Mindoro, Philippines, April 1945; VHP2006/8.III.10
    - George England in cockpit testing the engines. Mindoro island, Philippines., April 1945; VHP2006/8.III.11
    - Control tower at air strip. Palawan, Philippines, May 1945; VHP2006/8.III.12
    - Photos of Landing crafts taken from the air. Palawan, Philippines, June 1945; VHP2006/8.III.13
    - Army Airforce P-38 airplane at a shared airstrip with Navy Squadron. Mindoro, Phillipines, March 1945; VHP2006/8.III.14
    - Ancient Shell Back initiation for Navy Airmen who crossed equator. Palawan, Phillippines, May 1945; VHP2006/8.III.15
    - At Camp Kearny (San Diego, California) before going to Hawaii, 1945; VHP2006/8.III.16
      From L -R: Bill Weir, Glenn Light, George England, Mel Buhl Holzer
    - Mel Buhlholzer and George England with Philippine Monkey and Puppy. Palawan, Phillipines, June 1945; VHP2006/8.III.17
    - Filipino family happy to see Americans. Leyte, Phillipines, February 1945; VHP2006/8.III.18
    - checking oil level on PB4Y-1 (B-24 variants) Leyte, Phillipines, February 1945; VHP2006/8.III.19
      From L - R: Zeke Steine, George England, Roy Langford
    - Art work found on most planes done by Airforce techs for a few dollars. Leyte, Phillipines, March 1945; VHP2006/8.III.20
  - Subseries B: Moving Images, VHP2006/8.IIIb
    - Oral history interview with George W. England, Apr. 8, 2006; VHP2006/8.IIIb.1; Pereira, Lisa (Disk DVD VHP2006/8, Box VHP Interview 2006)